Guide to the Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records, 1953-2000 MSS 1002
Heinz History Center
Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records
1953-2000
Heinz History Center
Nelkin, Bob.
MSS 1002
4.5 linear feet (5 boxes + shelf)
First formed in 1951, the Allegheny County Chapter of the Pennsylvania Association for Retarded Children was established as a grassroots organization comprised of the parents of people with disabilities. The aspect of ACC-PARC's daily activities most represented in these records are the efforts of the association to investigate the treatment of people with disabilities at residential care facilities in Western Pennsylvania during the 1960s and 1970s. The Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records is housed in five boxes and arranged into four series and several subseries. Primarily comprised of correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, case files, notes, and news clippings, the records in this collection reflect the disability advocacy initiatives undertaken by ACC-PARC members throughout the late 1960s and 1970s. A portion of this collection has been digitized and can be found online.
History
First formed in 1951, the Allegheny County Chapter of the Pennsylvania Association for Retarded Children (ACC-PARC) was established as a grassroots organization comprised of the parents of people with disabilities. Operating under the name "the Greater Pittsburgh Association of Parents and Friends of the Mentally Retarded," this organization adopted a mission to "promote the general welfare of mentally retarded children of all ages everywhere." In 1956, the association reached non-profit status and changed its name to the Allegheny County Chapter of the Pennsylvania Association for Retarded Children (ACC-PARC) in order to reflect its affiliation with the statewide advocacy organization. In 1963, ACC-PARC was comprised of over 1,000 active members.
To fulfill its mission, ACC-PARC created a number of services to assist people with disabilities and their families, including diagnostic clinics, education and vocational training, community centers, ongoing research and advocacy efforts, counseling, and recreational activities. Counseling services offered by ACC-PARC often consisted of residential and educational referrals, case screenings, and care recommendations. ACC-PARC's advocacy efforts supported the association's vocational training programs centered on instructing people with disabilities how to perform tasks and become contributors in the workforce. ACC-PARC also chartered buses to facilitate site visits for the families of people with disabilities. In addition to providing ongoing services, ACC-PARC also regularly organized internal conventions to assess ongoing needs of people with disabilities in the region and regularly offered informative programs throughout the year.
To oversee and direct these activities, ACC-PARC was led by elected officers, a board of directors, and various committees, including Residential Care, State Affairs, Personnel, and Membership. Together with elected officers and board members, ACC-PARC's activities were also executed by the association's personnel, which included an executive director.
The aspect of ACC-PARC's daily activities most represented in these records are the efforts of the association to investigate the treatment of people with disabilities at residential care facilities in Western Pennsylvania during the 1960s and 1970s. Prompted by informal reports of mistreatment, ACC-PARC committee members developed a grassroots strategy to investigate the living conditions of people with disabilities at care facilities throughout the region. Overseen by staff member, Bob Nelkin, a small team of ACC-PARC members harnessed leads and reports to inform both announced and unannounced visits to care facilities such as Western State School and Hospital, the Polk Center, the Ridgeview Center, and the Highland Park Center. The leads and reports received by ACC-PARC members often originated from both the parents of residents as well as residential care workers. The visitation teams paid particular attention to residents' living conditions, facility staffing data, sanitary conditions, disciplinary practices, and treatment strategies. Recording their observations directly following their visit, the visitation team then generated formalized notes and reports that reflected their findings. Throughout the course of their visits, the visitation teams discovered that various facilities throughout the region employed the use of strait jackets, restraints, isolation rooms, cattle prods, and other abuses that violated the residents' human rights.
With their observations in hand, ACC-PARC members exposed the inadequacies they discovered by opening communications with a number of entities, including local government legislators, the secretary of the Pennsylvania State Department of Public Welfare (DPW) and members of the local media. In adopting this strategy, ACC-PARC members worked to expose adverse living conditions of people with disabilities in order to affect legislative change that either terminated inadequate care facilities or instituted reform in resident care and staffing.
During his tenure, Bob Nelkin served as associate director of ACC-PARC under executive director Chuck Peters and oversaw the organization's various initiatives, including the residential care facility site visits, the Alternatives to Institutions initiative, the Community Living Arrangement program, and other disability advocacy activities. In this role, Nelkin often corresponded closely with ACC-PARC members, the Pa. State Department of Public Welfare, and local government leaders in order to advance ACC-PARC initiatives.
The chief resident care facilities visited by the team of ACC-PARC members were the Polk Center and the Western State School and Hospital. In some cases, the visitation teams discovered human rights violations such as the use of wooden cages, battery prods, straightjackets, and other restraints. Throughout the early 1970s, ACC-PARC members discovered and exposed inadequate living conditions of residents at the Polk Center. The state of living conditions at Polk as exposed by ACC-PARC visitation team prompted the secretary of the Department of Public Welfare, Helene Wohlgemuth, to make an impromptu visit to the care facility. The conditions she witnessed prompted her to call for the immediate resignation of the Polk Center's superintendent, Dr. James H. McClelland, Jr. The organization's efforts to raise awareness of these conditions prompted an improvement in resident care, including the termination of the use of cages.
The ACC-PARC visitation team turned their attention to living conditions at the Western State School and Hospital (WSSH) throughout the early 1970s. Of primary concern to ACC-PARC members and other visitation task force members were the overcrowded conditions they discovered at the WSSH. As a result of their investigations, ACC-PARC associate executive director, Bob Nelkin published an essay "Death: A Way of Life," that shed light on the recent deaths of WSSH residents caused by staffing deficiencies, negligence, and mistreatment. ACC-PARC's partnership with Washington County Coroner Farrell Jackson sparked a formal joint visitation task force team comprised of mental health professionals in 1974. The notes and reports generated by this task force as well as ACC-PARC visitation team members did much to raise awareness across the state of the deficiencies at WSSH. In addition to reporting and publicizing the adverse conditions at WSSH, ACC-PARC also engaged in legal battles in order to stymie any court attempts to mandate the admission of new residents to WSSH.
In keeping with the mission of their advocacy efforts in Western Pa., ACC-PARC members closely followed the course of a 1974 federal class action lawsuit filed against the Pennhurst State School and Hospital, a residential care facility for the intellectually disabled in Spring City, Pa. Referred to as Halderman vs. Pennhurst State School and Hospital, this case argued that the deplorable living conditions of residents at Pennhurst was in violation of the Pa. Mental Health/Mental Retardation Act of 1966 as well as the Eighth and Fourteenth Amendments. Decisions in both the state district (1977) and circuit courts (1979) mandated the closure of Pennhurst and the dispersal of residents to smaller community living facilities. ACC-PARC ardently supported this decision to remove people with disabilities from institutions such as Pennhurst in favor of alternative living arrangements such as group homes and community living arrangements. As a consequence, ACC-PARC members under the direction of Bob Nelkin sustained pressure on state leaders, including Governor Dick Thornburgh, to implement court orders. In 1981, the United State Supreme Court ruled that it could not mandate the dispersal of Pennhurst residents due to the fact that it could not order state officials to observe state laws. Due to this decision, Pennhurst was not closed until December of 1987. Despite this, the Halderman vs. Pennhurst decision still set a precedent that people with disabilities had the right to live in community. In addition to mandating the dispersal of residents, the presiding judge also ordered that reports be conducted to document the adjustment of Pennhurst residents to community living arrangements.
As a result of their visits to the residential care facilities such as WSSH and the Polk Center, ACC-PARC began to advocate for community living arrangements as a viable alternative to institutionalization for people with disabilities. Members embraced debates surrounding zoning for these smaller community living arrangements and underscored the approach of these group homes to cultivate skills among residents.
In 1981, ACC-PARC complied with its parent organization's name change and became the Association for Retarded Citizens (ARC) of Allegheny County. In 1992, the organization once again followed the lead of its umbrella entity and became the Arc Allegheny. Arc Allegheny was later combined with the Arc of Beaver County to become the Arc of Greater Pittsburgh. As of the writing of this finding aid, the Arc of Greater Pittsburgh, the Arc of Westmoreland County, the ACHIEVA Support, and the ACHIEVA Family Trust were children organizations of ACHIEVA.
Scope and Content Notes
The Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records is housed in five boxes and arranged into four series and several subseries. Primarily comprised of correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, case files, notes, and news clippings, the records in this collection reflect the disability advocacy initiatives undertaken by ACC-PARC members throughout the late 1960s and 1970s. Among the collection's strengths are the materials in Series II, which contain the records created by ACC-PARC members throughout the course of their efforts to expose social welfare concerns in the residential care facilities they visited in the early 1970s. Series designations consist of Series I. Administrative Records (1953-1983), State School and Hospital (SSH) and Interim Care Committee Records (1972-1997), Series III: Scrapbooks (1966-1975), and Series IV: Photographs (1955-2000).
Arrangement
The Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records is arranged into four series and several subseries.
Series I: Administrative Records (1953-1983)
Subseries 1: Topical Files (1975-1982)
Series II: State School and Hospital (SSH) and Interim Care Committee Records (1972-1997)
Subseries 1: Pennhurst State School and Hospital (1954-1984)
Subseries 2: Western State School and Hospital (WSSH) (1967-1984)
Subseries 3: Polk Center (1966-1997)
Subseries 4: State Schools and Hospitals (SSH) and Interim Care Facilities (1972-1984
Subseries 5: Research (1966-1981
Series III: Scrapbooks (1966-1975)
Series IV: Photographs (1955-2000)
Conditions Governing Access
Due to the personal information disclosed, case file records have been restricted. Redacted copies of these case file records have been generated and interfiled with the collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift from George Pashel in 2013.
Archives accession # 2013.0173
Related Materials
Pennsylvania Association for Retarded Children, Allegheny County Chapter Records, 1952-1965, AIS.1966.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh.
From Wrongs to Rights video, https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xhvbc55L89I
Existence and Location of Copies
A portion of this collection has been digitized and can be found online.
Social service--Pennsylvania--Pittsburgh; Social welfare--Pennsylvania--Pittsburgh; Disability and the disabled--Pennsylvania--Pittsburgh; Disability law--Pennsylvania; People with disabilities--Abuse of--Pennsylvania; People with disabilities--Abuse of--Reporting--Pennsylvania; Polk (Pa.); Pittsburgh (Pa.); Canonsburg (Pa.); Spring City (Pa.); Nelkin, Bob.; Thornburgh, Dick. (1932-); Thornburgh, Ginny.; Jackson, Farrell.; Polk State Center (Polk, Pa.); Pennhurst State School and Hospital (Spring City, Pa.); Western Center (Canonsburg, Pa.); Highland Park Care Center (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Ebensburg State Center (Ebensburg, Pa.); Selinsgrove State Center (Selinsgrove, Pa.)
- Administrative Records, 1953-1983; I.
  Scope and Contents
  This series is comprised of records such as historical information files, member lists, manuals, correspondence, meeting minutes, notes, reports, program files, civil action suit records, annual plans, speeches, event flyers, newsletters and news clippings that document the administrative activities of ACC-PARC.
  The meeting minutes in this series record the functions of various ACC-PARC committees in the 1950s, including the executive board, legal, clinic, and community conference. Correspondence (1975-1983) primarily pertains to ACC-PARC's role in the disability advocacy movement, addressing topics such as the Bill of Rights, Social Security benefits, and behavioral shaping programs. Primary correspondents include local government leaders and the DPW.
  Reports include an analysis on Pennsylvania's program for the intellectually disabled (1973) and advocacy reports (1970s). Also included are written speeches (1975-1985) delivered by Gov. Milton Shapp, DPW secretaries Frank Beal and Helen O'Bannon, Ginny Thornburgh, and Allegheny County Commissioner Tom Foerster.
  - ACC-PARC Historic Information Written by Sara Settler, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - PARC History and Case Study of Social Change Movement, c. 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Officer and Board Member Lists, 1966-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board and Staff Manual, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Presidents Notes, c. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clinic Committee Meeting Minutes, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Community Conference Meeting Minutes, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Legal Committee Minutes, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Regarding Bill of Rights, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Recent Litigation Memo, July 11, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11, Item 1)
      A PARC internal memo that summarizes recent litigation that impacts the lives of residents of state institutions.
  - Correspondence (Bob Nelkin) Regarding Recognition, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letter from Peter Polloni to Bob Nelkin, March 11, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12, Item 1)
      A letter from Peter Polloni, executive director of PARC, thanking Bob Nelkin for forwarding reports and other information to him and to the United States Justice Department.
  - Correspondence (Bob Nelkin) Regarding Behavioral Shaping Programs, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letter to Frank Beal from Families and Friends of Southwest Rehabilitation Center, August 19, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13, Item 1)
      A letter from Families and Friends of Southwest Rehabilitation Center expressing the need for the creation of a behavioral management unit at the institution.
    - Letter from families of patients at Southwest Rehabilitation Center to Bob Nelkin, July 27, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13, Item 2)
      A letter requesting Bob Nelkin's advice on advocating for a behavioral care unit at Southwest Rehabilitation Center.
  - Correspondence Regarding DPW Policy, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence (Bob Nelkin) Regarding Social Security Benefits, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence (Bob Nelkin), 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ACC-PARC Recent Benefits to Families Memo, March 28, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item 1)
      Correspondence from Bob Nelkin to Joan Murdoch listing recent developments that have benefited parents of disabled children.
  - Correspondence (Bob Nelkin) Regarding MH/MR Program, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Ellen Siciliano, April 11, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17, Item 1)
      A letter from Bob Nelkin to Ellen Siciliano regarding a new center for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities in the Monongahela Valley area.
    - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Representative Richard J. Cessar, March 29, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17, Item 2)
      A letter from Bob Nelkin to Representative Richard Cessar voicing the concerns of citizens and ACC-PARC regarding a lack of services for citizens with intellectual and developmental disabilities and the emotionally disturbed.
  - Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letter from Teddi Leiden to Dottie Rowe on Department of Public Welfare Hiring Practices, May 25, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 18, Item 1)
      A letter from Teddi Leiden of ARC Pennsylvania to Dottie Rowe of the Office of Mental Retardation in the Department of Public Welfare regarding the state's hiring practices that led to the employment of individuals who mistreated residents.
  - PA Licensed Private Facilities List, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Reports: An Analysis of Pennsylvania's Program for the Mentally Retarded, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - ACC-PARC Community and Chapter Affairs Program Summary, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Program Summary Community and Chapter Affairs Division, November 1974 (Box 1, Folder 21, Item 1)
      A summary created by ACC-PARC of the existing educational programs, residential care, recreational activities, legislation, and funding for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities.
  - ACC-PARC Action Plan for Community Services, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - PARC Action Plan for Community Services, October 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22, Item 1)
      A copy of the PARC Action Plan designed to create and ensure superior community residential services for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities.
  - Advocacy Reports and Notes, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - ACC-PARC Advocacy Report, March 21, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23, Item 1)
      A report detailing recent actions and advocacy initiatives undertaken by ACC-PARC.
    - Proclamation of Retarded Children's Week Commonwealth of Pennsylvania Governor's Proclamation, November 14, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 23, Item 2)
      A copy of the official proclamation from Governor Scranton's office announcing Retarded Children's Week.
    - Monitoring of Community Living Arrangements in Allegheny County, May 22, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23, Item 3)
      A draft of a policy designed to monitor and improve community living arrangements in Allegheny County. Includes monitoring methods, funding of monitoring, rationale, and expected results.
  - Advocacy Slide Presentation, c. 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Advocacy Program Description, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - PL 41-142: Education of All Handicapped Children Act Integration Imperative Report, c. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - ACC Mental Health, Mental Retardation Program Annual Plan Development, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Letter from Joan Murdoch to Charles Peters, March 23, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 27, Item 1)
      A letter from Joan Murdoch of ACC-PARC to Charles Peters asking about Allegheny County's MH/MR plan for programs, training programs, and respite care. This letter is a follow up of the meeting Peters had with family members on February 16.
  - DPW MR Budget Analysis, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - DPW Governor Milton Shapp Address, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - DPW: Frank Beal Written Address: Challenge, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Excerpt from 1975 Department of Public Welfare Publication Challenge, November-December 1975 (Box 1, Folder 30, Item 1)
      A copy of the November-December 1975 issue of the Department of Public Welfare's Challenge magazine. Topics discussed include community living alternatives, DPW finances, health care, opportunities for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities, and events at state institutions.
    - Excerpt from 1976 Department of Public Welfare Publication Challenge, November-December 1976 (Box 1, Folder 30, Item 2)
      A copy of the November-December 1976 issue of the Department of Public Welfare's Challenge magazine. Topics discussed include opportunities for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities, community living alternatives, DPW finances, and events at state institutions.
    - Excerpt from 1977 Department of Public Welfare Publication Challenge, November-December 1977 (Box 1, Folder 30, Item 3)
      A copy of the November-December 1977 issue of the Department of Public Welfare's Challenge magazine. This issue includes an introductory letter from Secretary Frank Beal and an interview with Peter Polloni.
    - Excerpts from 1978 Department of Public Welfare Publication Challenge, January-February 1978 (Box 1, Folder 30, Item 4)
      A copy of the January-February 1978 issue of the Department of Public Welfare's Challenge magazine. This issue includes sections that discuss Community Living Arrangements, Family Resource Services, Early Intervention, and Vocational Rehabilitation.
  - DPW: Frank Beal Remarks to PARC May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Speech by The Honorable Frank S. Beal Secretary of Public Welfare at the Mercer County Association for the Retarded, INC. Annual Dinner, May 20, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 31, Item 1)
      A copy of a speech by Frank S. Beal given at the Mercer County Association for the Retarded's Annual Dinner. The speech discusses the future of care for people with disabilities. Beal focuses on the unsustainability of institutions and the need to transition to more community-based residential programs.
  - DPW: Frank Beal Remarks to PARC November 1976 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - ACC-PARC News Request for Coverage, November 9, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 32, Item 1)
      An ACC-PARC News announcement requesting press coverage for Frank S. Beal's follow-up visit. The third in a series of meetings on a lack of programs, services, and facilities.
    - ACC-PARC News Release, 1976 Beal Visit, November 4, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 32, Item 2)
      A press release from ACC-PARC about the upcoming visit from Frank S Beal of the Department of Public Welfare. ACC-PARC urges families and community members to attend to show their support for alternatives to institutions.
    - ACC-PARC Request for Coverage, Dr. Frank Menolascino, November 2, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 32, Item 3)
      An ACC-PARC request for media coverage of the visit of NARC (National Association for the Retarded) president, Dr. Frank Menolascino. Dr. Frank Menolascino was scheduled to speak in Pittsburgh and to receive the Institute of Pennsylvania Hospital Award in recognition of his advocacy for individuals with intellectual and developmental disabilities. ACC-PARC hoped to use his visit to draw attention to alternatives to institutionalization.
  - DPW: Frank S. Beal Testimony, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Ginny Thornburgh Speech and News Clipping Regarding Advocacy, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Governor Thornburgh Address on Human Services, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)